A Guide to the The Papers of the Joseph Carrington Cabell Family ca. 1783-1887
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Joseph Carrington Cabell Family ca. 1783-1887
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-111-c
This collection consists of ca. 4,200 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were given to the University of Virginia Library by Robert Self, Wingina, Virginia, on January 18, 2001.
Biographical/Historical Information
Nicholas Cabell (1750-1803), of "Liberty Hall," Nelson County, Virginia, married Hannah Carrington Cabell (1751-1817) in 1772, and had the following children: 1) William H. Cabell (1772- 1853) m. Elizabeth Cabell (d. 1801) in 1795 and m. Agnes S.B. Gamble in 1805 2) Dr. George Cabell (1774-1827) m. Susanna Wyatt (d.1817) in 1798 and m. Eliza Fitzhugh May (1794-1859) 3) Elizabeth Cabell (1776-1802) m. Dr. William B. Hare (1760-1818) in 1793 4) Joseph Carrington Cabell (1778-1856) m. Mary Walker Carter (d.1863) in 1807 5) Nicholas Cabell, Jr. (1780-1809) m. Margaret Read Venable (1782-1857) in 1802 6) Mary Anne Cabell (1783- 1850) m. Captain Benjamin Carrington (1768-1838) in 1804 7) Mayo Carrington Cabell (1784 Aug-1784 Sep) 8) Hannah Cabell (1786-1794) 9) Heningham Cabell (1787-1794) 10) Paul C. Cabell (1791 May-1791 June)
Nathaniel Francis Cabell (1807-1891), son of Nicholas and Margaret Venable Cabell, married Anne Blaws Cocke (1811-1862), daughter of John Hartwell Cocke, in 1831. He married Mary M. Kellar of Baltimore in 1867. Anne Cocke and N.F. Cabell had the following children: 1) Frances Hartwell Cabell (1833-1844) 2) Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell (1834-1863) m. in 1855, her cousin, William D. Cabell 3) Philip Barraud Cabell (1836- ) m. in 1861, Julia Calvert Bolling ("Pinkie"), daughter of Thomas and Mary Louisa Morris Bolling; during the Civil War, he served on the staff of his uncle, General Philip St. George Cocke, Confederate States of America 4) Sallie Faulcon Cabell 5) Frances Grace Cabell (1852- ) m. in 1876, her cousin, R. Kenna Campbell 6) Cary Charles Cabell (1854-1856)
Joseph Carrington Cabell (1778-1856), born in Nelson County, Virginia, to Colonel Nicholas and Hannah Carrington Cabell, was a Virginia legislator and president of the James River and Kanawha Company. A graduate of William and Mary (1798), he married Mary Carter in 1807. Cabell was a member of the Virginia House of Delegates in 1809 and 1831-1835, where he was instrumental in establishing the Literary Fund and the Virginia Senate 1810-1829, where he obtained legislative support and financial appropriations for the University of Virginia, established in Charlottesville, Virginia, by Thomas Jefferson. For thirty-seven years, he also served as a member of the Board of Visitors and Rector.
Scope and Content Information
These papers consist primarily of the correspondence of Joseph Carrington Cabell and other Cabell and allied family members, ca. 1783-1887, ca. 4,200 items (12 Hollinger boxes, 5 linear feet). Among the correspondents are the Reverend George Bush, Anne Blaws Cocke Cabell, Elizabeth Nicholas Cabell, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, Philip Barraud Cabell, Sally F. Cabell, William H. Cabell, John Coalter, Cary Charles Cocke, John Hartwell Cocke, Lucy Oliver Cocke, Philip St. George Cocke, Isaac A. Coles, the Reverend Richard De Charms, Isaac Read, Judge Francis Nathaniel Watkins, and others.
Also included are some legal and financial papers and correspondence of the Bolling family, and some relating to the James River and Kanawha Canal Company. Other legal and financial papers include papers concerning the estates of William Newburn, Sarah R. Newburn and William C.R. Newburn, with William Bolling Executor, and James Lownes.
Other papers present in the collection include news clippings, with a separate folder of ones devoted to Professor George Bush (1796-1859) of the New Jerusalem Church; manuscripts by Nathaniel Francis Cabell; poetry; school reports of Sallie F. Cabell and Fannie G. Cabell; and a copy of a draft of a report, in an unknown hand, on the First Battle of Bull Run, originally submitted by Philip St. George Cocke to General Beauregard. For a full copy of this report by Cocke to Beauregard, please see the Cocke Family Papers, #640, Box 165, dated August 3, 1861.
Summaries of the content of each group of correspondence follows immediately in the guide, in the order of their appearance in the folder listing, beginning with the first series consisting of correspondence to and from Joseph C. Cabell.
The first series in this collection consists of the correspondence of Joseph Carrington Cabell arranged alphabetically according to the last name of the correspondent. The correspondence from Edward Carrington Cabell to Joseph C. Cabell is chiefly concerned with his father's health and an invitation to his uncle to visit him.
Hannah Carrington Cabell writes to her son, Joseph and his new wife, Mary (also called "Polly") at the beginning of their marriage in 1807, chiefly about domestic news and concerns, including discussions of household furnishings, weaving wool, and other household and clothing needs. Hannah Cabell resided at "Harewood" following the death of her husband and daughter to care for her granddaughters. She often refers to the poor health of Dr. Hare and other family members.
Hannah Cabell also refers to a slave sale from the estate of Samuel [Wenfrey?] (1808 Oct 23 and Nov 3); the poor health of her son and his brother, Nicholas (1808 Dec 28; 1809 Jun 17); arrangements made for the summer clothes of the slaves and work on Joseph's house waiting for the arrival of the carpenter (1810 Jun 19); her purchase of one slave boy eleven years old (1811 Feb 12); a slave, John, who ran away after being punished with a switch by his master (1812 Mar 29); her trip to Warm Springs and White Sulphur Springs (1812 Aug 11); brief references to the War of 1812, including "our late and glorious victories," perhaps on Lake Erie (1813 Oct 3) and the peace negotiations (1815 Mar 5); requests for four or five dozen bottles of port wine for the health of Dr. Hare (1816 Mar 1); the runaway slave of Dr. Hare, [Leroy?], son of Toby at "Bon Aire" (1816 Jun 23); request for Joseph to attend a slave auction in Richmond for her on January 2nd to purchase a lad of fifteen or sixteen, able to handle a plow (1816 Dec 16 and 30); and the death of the wife of General John Hartwell Cocke, Ann Blaws (1817 Jan 26).
The correspondence of Dr. John Grattan Cabell (1817-1896) is chiefly concerned with business conducted for his uncle but also mentions a cholera epidemic at Richmond (1854 July 13); and the death of his wife, Sarah Marshal Tankersley, leaving him with a daughter, Sarah Elizabeth Cabell (1855 Apr 7).
The correspondence of Joseph C. Cabell to John H. Cocke, 1810-1848 (5 folders), reveals many details of this deep and long-lasting friendship between these two men, including much personal news, details of their agricultural pursuits, and requests for help or advice. There are few references to his work with the University of Virginia, except general mentions of the meetings of the Board of Visitors. There is also little political content, except for references to his interest in internal improvements and the James River and Kanawha Canal Company.
Occasionally, there are a few letters to or from the wives of the two men in these folders and they have been kept with the letters of their husbands. These include one from Joseph C. Cabell to Anne B. Cocke, wife of John H. Cocke (1810 Aug 5), and several letters from Mary W. Cabell to the Cockes (November 11 and December 17, 1816).
Among the topics in the letters from the first folder from Cabell to Cocke are: discussion of the Corotoman Plantation, Lancaster County, Virginia, and the settlement of the Estate (1811 Jan 11; 1812 Sep 20, Nov 16, Dec 15 and 16; 1813 Jan 16); the names and prices of slaves from Corotoman Plantation sold for "incorrigible conduct" (1813 Jan 5); his support for Colonel James Monroe in the next race for governor (1811 Jan 11); agricultural improvements and his plans to introduce the "Albemarle system" at Edgewood, Nelson County, Virginia (1811 Jun 3); seeks advice about hiring a new overseer (1814 Aug 8); news of the reappearing of the enemy in the Chesapeake Bay (1814 Nov 3); the Howard's Land scheme (1815 Jul 3 and 11); requests for Cocke's assistance in the selection of new slaves, fearing the "hardiness of the lowland Negroes" (1816 Jun 10); mention of a runaway slave, named Abraham, originally from Corotoman (1816 Aug 22); the deteriorating health of Ann B. Cocke (1816 Dec 20 and 26) her death (1817 Jan 2); and his plans to build an enclosure for the graveyard (1819 Jun 26).
Topics in the second folder to Cocke include: recommendation of Millwrights Guide by Oliver Evans (1820 Aug 23); requests that Cocke's man, Peter, initiate Cabell's slave Quintilian "into the arcana of his shop, he has a great desire to advance himself in his beloved art" and mentions another slave, Will, from Corotoman who has come up to see the mountains and "to be cured of the habit of running away." He also mentions improvements in his barn designed by the machinist Andrew Duncan and Cocke's upcoming marriage to Louisa Maxwell Holmes (all of the above in letter, 1821 Jun 9).
Many of his letters in 1821 and 1822 discuss his unhappiness with his current overseer, whose mismanagement has already cost him a good deal, his attempts to hire a new overseer, and his despair that the machinist Duncan will ever complete his work at Cabell's farm (1821 Jul 8, 29; Aug 10; Sep 16; Nov 22; 1822 Sep 6-7; Oct 24 and 31). Cabell also praises the superior work of Cato, a slave belonging to J.H. Cocke, on his mill (1822 Aug 24). Other topics include his brother's financial difficulties (1821 Sep 21, Oct 4); and the destruction by fire of one of his barns with 200 barrels of corn at Corotoman (1822 Mar 13).
He expresses his concern over the possible loss of his farm book for 1822, his accounts of his expenditures for his mill and barn, and his last settlement with Duncan (1823 Jul 9) and his gladness that he purchased "Midway" despite the opposition of his family (1824 Jun 15). He discusses his improvements at "Edgewood" and skilled slave laborers carrying out the work (1825 Jul 22, 26; Aug 6); the death of Edmund Harrison of Amelia County (1826 Feb 5); and praise for John Cocke, son of John Hartwell Cocke (1825 Jul 22).
In the third folder to Cocke, Cabell discusses the progress on and hopes for the James River and Kanawha Canal (1824 Aug 15, 22, 28; Sep 23; 1826 Oct 15) and Claudius Crozet in reference to the Canal (1824 Jun 20 and Nov 8; 1826 Sep 2). He also feels the pressure of trying to sell the land belonging to his brother George (1826 Sep 2). He also describes his religious practice (1828 Aug 21) and his preparations for the construction of his ice house (1828 Oct 27). Cabell refers to the meeting of the Board of Public Works in Richmond and the discussion of the [Internal Improvement?] Convention Question in the House of Delegates, which he fears will not result in any extension of internal improvements (1829 Jan 10). He includes a detailed discussion of several types of wheat harvesting machines, their designs and merits (1829 Dec 15).
The fourth and fifth folders of correspondence to Cocke contain several references to his interests in the James River and Kanawha Canal Company. Among these are: the delay in opening up the stock subscription until the August Court (1832 Aug 7); the meeting of the stockholders (1835 May 15); the visit of the committee composed of members of both houses in the Virginia Legislature investigating the affairs of the company (1843 Jan 25); descriptions of damages to the canal and other matters concerning its operation (1843 Apr 19; 1844 Jan 25, Mar 28); a discussion of the desire of Governor McDowell to transfer the James River and Kanawha Canal Company and its works to the state (1843 Nov 10); and the strong railroad interests acting against the James River and Kanawha Canal Company (1847 Dec 5).
Other topics in these two folders to Cocke include: the death of "our dear beloved child" at the Sweet Springs on October 12, 1839, and its devastating effects upon the Cabells (1839 Oct 18); the death of the second Mrs. Cocke, Louisa Maxwell Holmes Cocke (1843 Jun 9); an extract from a report of engineer Edward Miller on the "Improvement of the Schuylkill Navigation" (1845 May 5); temperance (1845 Jul 20); and the damage from hailstones on his two upper farms at "Midway" (1848 Jul 17). This completes the summary of letters in the first box.
The first two folders in the second box contain letters from Joseph C. Cabell to Isaac A. Coles of "Green Mountain," Albemarle County, and secretary to President Thomas Jefferson, chiefly pressing Coles to visit. Other topics include an attempt to procure wine from Coles for his brother and Mr. Wirt (1807 Jul 26); and Cabell asking Coles about the condition of affairs with England, telling him not to purchase a gig for him, if war is coming (1807 Nov 18 and 1808 Sep 21). Also present is one letter from William H. Cabell to John Coles concerning the health of his son, Isaac Coles (1804 Sep 30) and one letter from Charles J. Cabell seeking a government position (1808 Oct 28).
The second group of letters to Coles give advice to him concerning his courtship of a Miss Brown in Williamsburg (1810 Nov 29, Dec 21; 1811 Jan 14); the political attack upon Cabell at the Capitol by his enemies (1813 Mar 21); and references to the military service of Coles on the Canadian frontier (1813 Jun 27; 1816 Oct 19).
There are two folders of notes and letters from Joseph C. Cabell to his nephew, Nathaniel Francis Cabell, which includes one note from Peggy R. Cabell. These are chiefly miscellaneous notes requesting N.F. Cabell to copy documents, perform many different tasks, and giving him proxy instructions and other directions. Specific topics include the death of cousin Mayo Cabell's daughter, Eliza (1849 May 10); dissatisfaction with the behavior of his slaves (1851 Jan 1); another reference to slaves (1851 Jan 1); a discussion of the upkeep of the road from Warminster to Rockfish (1851 Aug 29); and in two notes with no year given, an apparent list of slave names (n.y. Feb 8) and list of damages to his crops from Frank's bull (n.y. Aug 12).
In the folder of correspondence from Joseph C. Cabell to his parents and brother, George, he chiefly discusses his trip to South Carolina (1801 Dec-1802 Mar 19); a trip to the Warm Springs (1802 Jun 23); the death of his sister, Betsy (1802 Dec 11) and his wait at Norfolk, Virginia, for a ship to France (1802 Dec 11 and 23).
His letters to Judge St. George Tucker (1807-1819) all concern the management of the Corotoman estate. The Corotoman estate is also a topic in the letters of Joseph C. Cabell to William Wirt (1823 Mar 15), among other business matters. The letters of Landon Cabell all concern business matters involving both himself and Joseph C. Cabell.
Dr. Robert G. Cabell's letters contain family news and medical advice, particularly for Oscar, [a slave?] (1842 May 26) and a report on the medical condition of a slave named Moses, who was examined by Dr. Cabell (1847 Dec 20).
The remainder of the folders in Box 2 contain letters from William H. Cabell to his brother, Joseph H. Cabell. From 1803 until May 1806, Joseph C. Cabell is traveling in Europe. Folder one of the correspondence from William H. Cabell to Joseph Cabell contains the following topics: the death of their sister, Elizabeth Cabell Hare (1802 Dec 7); references to renewed war between France and England and details about the death of their father (1803 Aug 23); details regarding the murder of Doctor James Hopkins (1803 Dec 10); political news in Virginia (1803 Dec 10); reference to the trial of Aaron Burr drawing to a close (1807 Oct 19); a warning for Joseph not to move to Corotoman (1807 Nov 19, 21); William's eagerness to leave the position of governor (1807 Dec 1); William's wish to call on Thomas Jefferson while he is at Monticello on his return to Richmond (1808 Jul 26); and his request for any of the Corotoman "gang" male slaves, and instructions to Joseph to send "old Sam" because his wife is at "Repton" (1808 Oct).
Topics in the second folder of correspondence from William to Joseph Cabell include: William's desire to acquire two slaves "old Fanny" from Captain Carrington and "old Sam" from his brother, Joseph (1810 Jan 9); a discussion of the court and legal system in Virginia and the practice of runaway slaves who arm themselves and collect in groups to form camps underground or in caves (1810 Dec 31); and a discussion about whether Joseph should go into the ranks of the military near the beginning of the War of 1812, where William advises him to secure a substitute and also not to take a professorship (1812 Jun 15, 22, 28).
Topics in the third folder of correspondence from William to Joseph Cabell includes: an opinion that the greatest danger from the British forces lies on the water not on land (1813 Mar 26); a rumor about Napoleon Bonaparte that he read in the Charleston Gazette(1814 Jun 2); advice about the slaves at Corotoman (1814 Jul 7); difficulties of William with his son, Nicholas, and a request for Joseph to advise Nicholas from his relationship as his uncle (1814 Sep 27; 1815 Jun 6; 1816 Apr 25); a discussion about the settlement of the Corotoman estate, including a letter from Joseph to William (1815 Oct 12 and 15); the sale of a slave, Becky, by the mother of William and Joseph (1817 Jul 12) and the death of Dr. William B. Hare at Harewood (1818 Jun 28).
The topics in the fourth folder of correspondence from William to Joseph Cabell include: a memorandum of slaves conveyed by W.C. Nicholas in trust for the benefit of William H. Cabell with their ages and other notes, as of the summer of 1819 (see the letter dated 1820 Oct 22); request to allow a slave called Johnson, the son of Grace, who was the cook for William to be sent to Joseph for training as a cook (1821 Aug 12); the death of William's son, Nicholas (1821 Oct 13); concern for the health of his son, Abraham Cabell (1821 Oct 21 and Nov 30); a reference to the argument between the Governor [Thomas Mann Randolph] and his Council, and a description of the Governor as "a high minded, independent and honorable man; but greatly deficient in good sense and discretion" (1821 Dec 20).
The topics in the fifth folder of correspondence from William to Joseph Cabell, which begins Box 3, include: his commiseration over their choice of bad overseers (1822 Jun 10); his concern over the initial disappearance of Robert Wirt, Abram Cabell's discovery of young Wirt at Lynchburg, Wirt's plan to go to the Western country to settle, and the last sighting of Wirt at the Giles Courthouse in Virginia (1822 Aug 15, 18, and Sep 8).
The sixth folder of their correspondence includes a recommendation for Colonel [Robert?] Gamble to be appointed Principal Engineer to the State by William H. Cabell (1823 Mar 28). Folder seven contains a note about sending up one of Abram Cabell's slaves, Judy, daughter of "Isbel" who lived on the plantation of Joseph Cabell (1825 Jun 21). Much of folder eight is taken up with discussions about the attempts of Abram Cabell to sell his land and the slave claim of Joseph Cabell (1827-1828). William also writes his advice to Joseph to sell "Midway" (1828 Aug 6); Henry Carrington and Abram Cabell have set off for Florida (1829 Apr 16); and his reason for keeping Robert [Gamble Cabell] at home was to allow "the commotion at college to subside" (1829 Apr 23).
Folder nine of correspondence from William to Joseph Cabell includes: a discussion of the terms of the will of Mrs. Tucker, drawn up by William (1835 May 31) and a discussion about the guardianship accounts of Miss Carter, kept by Joseph Cabell (1836 Apr 6). The tenth and last folder contains several letters, including one from Colonel Robert Gamble, about a serious illness of William (1840 Aug 28, Sep 9, and Nov 11).
Dr. George Callaway writes chiefly of business matters, including one letter from William Massie to himself, but also expresses concern over the death of Nicholas Cabell (1821 Oct 27).
Mathew Carey (1760-1839), Philadelphia publisher, asks if Joseph knows anyone who can help him distribute some pamphlets expressing his views on tariffs and protectionism (1829 Dec 14); describes his life and habits (1830 Jan 4); and remarks upon the "menacing state of affairs in South Carolina" stating that "The crisis demands all the energies of the friends of the human race. If we escape this danger, the union may be safe for half a century. But a little remissness may make shipwreck of all our hopes" (1830 Jul 22).
There are three folders of letters from Judge John Coalter (1769-1838) to Joseph Cabell, including two letters from St. George Coalter (1838-1839). Topics include: an offer of Coalter's brother to buy Cabell's slaves for a sugar plantation in New Orleans (1812 Sep 6); a warning not to sell Corotoman or its slaves in unsettled times of war (1814 Jun 27); the death of Susan, wife of Dr. George Cabell (1817 Jul 14); a mention of his nomination for Judge in the Court of Appeals (18[2?]0 Jan 14); his return from the wilderness, where he has built a "waterworks for washing out gold" (1830 Sep 22, Oct 14); nullification (1831 Aug 1); and a request for information about a proposed turnpike or railroad from the north branch of the Rappahannock to the Potomac (1832 Jan 30 and Mar 15; 1833 Apr 13; and 1834 Jan 20).
Box 4 contains nine folders of correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph Cabell, including three letters from Ann Blaws Cocke to Mary Cabell (1809 Dec 29; 1810 Feb 13 and Apr 4). These letters are full of personal news of family and friends, business affairs, discussions about agricultural practices, and advice.
Topics in the first three folders include: Merino sheep (1809 Jan 20); the confirmation of both William H. Cabell and John Coalter on the Court of Appeals (1811 Dec 10); the vote on the nomination of John Hartwell Cocke to the rank of Brigadier General ([ca. 1814]); notice that Cocke had been called into military service, his belief that an attack on Washington was imminent, and his estimate of the resources of the British available for such an attack (1814 Aug 23); the overthrow of Napoleon Bonaparte in France (1815 Aug 18); work on the Bremo house and its cornerstone laid (1816 Jul 18 and 1818 Jul 8); Cocke considered for the Board of Public Works (1818 Feb 16); a late snow upon the Blue Ridge Mountains (1818 May 4); a list of Cocke's innovative agricultural practices (1818 Jul 8); and a letter of Wilson J. Cary about his carpenter to Cocke, who forwarded it to Cabell (1818 Oct 19).
Topics in the fourth folder of correspondence from John Hartwell Cocke to Joseph Cabell include: religious counsel, which Cocke promises to send annually, the extremely cold weather, and his disinterest in serving as president of the Agricultural Society of Virginia, which he fears is becoming a "hot bed for hatching politics" (1820 Jan 17); river improvements and the success of his threshing machine (1820 Aug 1); discussion of other machinery and an earthquake (1820 Sep 1); the school at Bremo, full and doing well with Mr. [Cavadalli?] as its teacher (1820 Aug 1 and Sep 15); Cocke's pursuit of his second wife, Louisa Maxwell, in Norfolk (1821 Jun 6 and 23; Aug 13); advice to Cabell to sell Corotoman (1822 Mar 18); concern over the financial habits of his son, John, while a student (1822 May 13); and the death of Wilson Cary at Carysbrook (1823 Sep 12).